Who's there?
Keller.
Why are you here this time of night?
L... I wanted to pray.
Is something wrong?
I...
Can I help you in any way?
- Can I be of any help?
- No one can help me.
I have abused your kindness.
How?
You gave my wife and me
a home, a job, even friendship.
I felt you would let me
be your friend.
So wonderful a thing for a refugee,
a German, a man without a home.
- You will hate me now.
- I don't hate anyone, Keller.
You will, after what you
have done for me.
You trusted me.
You saw that my wife and I
were not common servants.
It was you who found more pleasant
tasks for us, working here in the rectory.
It was my wife, working so hard...
It breaks my heart.
What is the matter?
I must confess to you.
I must tell someone.
I want to make a confession.
I confess to almighty God
and to you, Father, that I have sinned.
- When was your last confession?
- I can't remember.
Can you remember approximately?
I have killed Mr. Villette.
Go on.
Villette, the lawyer.
I went to his house tonight.
I went to steal his money.
I wore a cassock to avoid attention.
He surprised me.
He was going to call the police.
I tried to stop him.
I didn't mean to kill him.
Alma, I'm not a murderer.
It was an accident.
It was the money.
How could I watch you work so hard?
I lie awake night after night...
...and I think, "All we need is $2000."
Alma, with $2000, we can
start a new life.
Villette was rich...
...but now I cannot keep it.
That's what Father Logan told me.
I must give it back. I promised him.
Oh, it's so hard, Alma.
It's so dangerous.
They will catch me.
They will hang me.
I cannot.
Father Logan will go to them.
He will tell them.
He will tell them?
He cannot tell them
what he heard in confession.
The police will come.
Why, Alma?
Why should they come here?
They know nothing.
I have told them nothing, have I?
- Alma, no one knows.
- Father Logan.
He cannot tell them what
he heard in the confessional.
Can't you understand that?
Otto.
- What is it, Alma?
- You're going to the police?
What is today, Alma?
Isn't it the day when I attend
to Mr. Villette's garden?
But he's dead.
I always work in Mr. Villette's
garden on Wednesdays.
Today is Wednesday, Alma.
- Good morning, Father Logan.
- Good morning, Father.
Tell me, will it take you and Keller...
...much longer to finish
the painting in this room?
I don't know.
I ask because the smell
makes one quite ill.
You know, I read some
advertisement about paints...
...and, of course, one shouldn't
judge on so little evidence, but l...
- After you, Father.
- One finds it difficult to believe...
...that there are paints with no smell.
Do you know of any paints
that do not smell, Father Michael?
Do I know...?
No, I don't.
Well, don't think of it.
It doesn't matter.
How fortunate we are
to have Keller with us.
The man is clever about everything.
Before he came six months ago...
...don't you remember how all
the drains wouldn't work...
...and the windows would not open?
One can learn a great deal from him.
Father Benoit and his bicycle
are in time for breakfast.
Good morning, Father Millars,
Father Michael.
- Good morning.
- Morning.
Seriously, must you keep your bicycle
in the hall, Father Benoit?
It doesn't always fall, and I don't
seem to know where else.
- It's lucky he doesn't have a horse.
- Would you pass me the butter, please?
Mrs. Keller, would you ask your husband
to look at my front tire?
- It's flat. Could you, please?
- My husband? But it is Wednesday.
- He's not here.
- Thank you, no.
On Wednesdays, he attends
to Mr. Villette's garden.
Then will you tell him
when he comes back, please?
Yes, Father, I'll tell him
when he comes back.
Now, now, Father Benoit,
you should learn how to patch a tire.
One should be able
to take care of one's possessions.
One has a face,
one would shave it.
- One has a...
- Excuse me, please.
Good morning, Father.
Monsieur Villette's been murdered.
Good morning.
- Good morning, Father.
- Good morning.
- I had an appointment here.
- Appointment?
With Villette? Well, he's dead.
Yes, I know. Is there anything I can do?
Well, perhaps Mr. Larrue would
like to see you. Come in, Father.
Mr. Larrue, sir. Father here says
he had an appointment with Villette.
I'll be with you in a moment.
Hello, Father.
- I believe I've met you before, haven't I?
- Yes, I'm from St. Marie.
- Yes. How is Father Millars?
- Father Millars is fine.
Good. You had an appointment
with Villette?
- Yes.
- Anything special?
- No.
- You've heard what's happened.
Father, Keller works
at the rectory, doesn't he?
Yes. He and his wife work there.
The poor devil is terrified
at the moment, Father.
Forgive me,
but I've forgotten your name.
- Logan.
- Father Logan.
You don't mind if we call on you today,
maybe tomorrow?
Perhaps we'd like to know what your
appointment with Villette was all about.
Murphy, get Keller.
He's the man who found the body.
- Mr. Larrue. No fingerprints.
- All right.
This was on his desk.
The keys were in his pocket.
Five hundred dollars.
It does not look like robbery, sir.
They usually take the lot.
- You work at the rectory at St. Marie's?
- Yes.
Good. Now, how did
you find the body?
On Wednesdays, I work
in Mr. Villette's garden.
This morning, I arrived
as usual at 8:30. I came inside...
- You have a key?
- No. The door was open.
- That frightened me.
- An open door?
- Why should that frighten you?
- The door was always locked.
I went in, and there he was.
I could see that he was dead.
- I wanted to run.
- Run?
There I was, a man without
a country, alone, discovering a murder.
I thought of the police.
I'm always afraid of the police.
- That's a German fear, this fear.
- There's nothing to be afraid of.
- Step outside for a moment.
- Yes. Thank you, sir.
- Villette's been murdered.
- He's dead? I can't believe it.
We're free.
Good morning.
Is my husband in the chamber?
Yes, madame. Mr. Grandfort
is speaking now. A very stormy debate.
That is the understatement of the year.
The honorable member
has used every known cliché...
...except perhaps "curb your dog,
keep your city clean."
Equal salary for female schoolteachers...
...would bring disaster
to our whole economy.
Except to the economy
of female schoolteachers.
- Mr. Speaker!
- At this point of the discussion...
...I adjourn the House
until this afternoon at 3:00.
Ruth, my dear,
what a charming surprise.
- Pierre, take me to lunch.
- Of course.
Feeling better, then? This morning,
you seemed rather depressed.
- Was I?
- Yes, and not only this morning.
- I don't seem depressed now, do I?
- No.
The tire wasn't flat after all.
Of course, you and Keller
know what you're doing.
Personally, I would have preferred
an old-fashioned white.
- That's what it is.
- Is it?
At least it's supposed to be.
- Oh, Mr. Keller, good morning.
- Good morning, Father.
You're back early, aren't you?
Is Mr. Villette's garden flourishing?
Mr. Villette is dead, Father.
- Dead?
- He was murdered, Father.
What? Did you hear that,
Father Logan? How dreadful.
I discovered the body.
I called the police.
Then they came and asked me
a lot of questions.
A lot of people were outside the house.
Then the inspector told me I could leave.
What a terrible thing.
A very terrible thing.
Father, why did you come
to Villette's house this morning?
Father, I must speak to you.
I know what you must think of me...
...but I can't give myself up. I can't.
They would hang me.
Hasn't God forgiven me, thanks to you?
But the police never would.
I don't know what you're
talking about.
But it was I who confessed to you.
It was my confession.
I want you to speak to me about it.
You must tell me what to do.
I can't give myself up.
You must tell me some other way.
There is nothing I can add
to what I've already said.
Aren't you human?
Haven't you ever been afraid?
You are so good.
It's easy for you to be good.
Have you no pity for me?
- Otto.
- Oh, Alma.
Otto, Father Benoit asked earlier...
...would you please
mend the tire on his bicycle?
But the tire wasn't flat
after all, Alma.
I don't see why you're so damn solemn
about this case, Larrue.
Anyway, why do you come
and worry me after lunch?
I've always had the greatest
admiration for you.
You have, in the past, been faced
with tremendously difficult cases...
...all of which you have solved
with remarkable skill.
And now, here you have
a case in which there are no clues...
...no fingerprints,
no motives, no suspects.
Ought to be very simple for you.
Shall I bring the girls in, sir?
- Girls?
- Yes.
Just a possibility.
It may be something to go on.
Sit down.
Sorry I had to drag you
away from school.
We love to be dragged away
from school. Thank you.
Are you a detective, monsieur?
Yes. And monsieur here
is the crown prosecutor.
Hello.
- Would you like a biscuit?
- Please.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome.
Now, my little ones,
tell me everything.
Your mother said that you
passed the Villette house last night.
- That's right.
- And what was the time?
- Eleven o'clock.
- No, it was after 11:O0.
- Well, now, which of you is right?
- Well, we had been babysitting...
...but we didn't go straight home.
That's why.
Well, shall we say, then,
between 11 and 11:30?
- Yes.
- And what did you see?
We saw someone
leaving the Villette house.
- A man or a woman?
- Man.
- Well, what was he like?
- He was a priest.
- What?
- A priest.
Now this is very important.
Are you sure?
Quite sure.
Tell us exactly.
On our way home by the Rue Valentine,
we passed Monsieur Villette's house.
We know it well. It was very dark,
and she was frightened.
- I was not.
- Yes, you were, and we began to hurry.
And then suddenly,
there was this priest.
He was coming out of the house
and walking away.
- Did you see his face?
- No.
How tall was he?
Like him.
- Was he fat or thin?
- Not fat. Not thin.
Did you notice anything special
about him?
- Did he see you?
- I don't think so.
But you are absolutely sure
he was a priest?
Yes.
Thank you. You may go now.
Oh, my little ones, I do not want you
to say anything to anyone about this.
- Promise.
- Yes.
Thank you.
Murphy, I want you to check
every rectory in town...
...and find out which priests
were out late last night.
Yes, sir.
Of course, it's absurd
that a priest would be involved.
You don't really think
it could be a priest?
Yes, maybe.
- Who?
- I have to make sure.
I can't tell you until
I've checked further.
Well, don't be so mysterious.
Most of his time is given
to his parishioners.
Was he with one on Tuesday night?
I have no idea where he was
or what he did...
...but I'm perfectly sure it's all right.
He will tell you so himself. Come in.
- Good evening, Father Logan.
- Good evening.
I believe this room has given this
gentleman from the police department...
...the idea that we hide grime with paint,
but it is not so, Mr. Murphy.
We have made certain that the walls
underneath are spotless.
I don't question that, Father.
Sorry to bother you, Father.
It's no bother. What can I do for you?
It seems that Inspector Larrue
wishes to speak to you.
Would it be convenient for you
to come down to the office now?
Certainly. Certainly.
It's all right, Father,
I told Mr. Larrue I'd be available.
Good night.
What is it, Father?
Who was that man?
The police want to ask
Father Logan some questions.
Oh, now you're bringing
your bicycle into the study.
How much further into the rectory
are you gonna push it?
- Alma, have you washed the cassock?
- Not yet.
- Where is it?
- It's in our room.
Don't wash it. I don't want it washed.
- But why?
- Listen to me.
I'm sorry to have kept you waiting.
I was occupied on the telephone.
It's all right, Murphy. I'll call you later.
- Unpleasant bit of business, isn't it?
- It is, yes.
Sit down.
Well, just a few questions,
and we'll get it over as soon as possible.
You've been at St. Marie's
for how long?
For nearly two years now.
I have known Father Millars for...
For a long while.
Matter of fact, I was a choirboy
when he was at the basilica.
Really?
I've heard that you saw military service
during the last war.
I believe you were awarded
the Military Cross. Yes.
You seem to have done
a number of brave things.
Well, I survived.
Are you given to understatement,
Father?
That depends.
This case, this Villette murder,
is all understatement so far.
- You knew Villette, didn't you?
- Slightly, yes.
Then perhaps you can help.
What was he like?
Well, unfortunately,
I didn't know him well.
Well, did you know him
socially or in a business way?
In neither way, actually.
I'd met him once many years ago.
- Cigarette?
- Thank you, no.
No one seems to have
known this Villette...
...and yet he was a lawyer.
He had clients.
Not one of his clients have any
information to give about the man.
Oh, not that you were a client of his,
as you say, you hardly knew him...
...but may I ask what were you going
to see him about yesterday morning?
Well, that was a personal matter.
You were acting for someone?
One of your parishioners, perhaps.
I can just say that my visit didn't have
anything to do with Villette's death.
Well, of course it didn't, Father.
But you do understand that I must
consider every scrap of information?
When a murder has been committed...
...each scrap of information
is important to the police.
- Of course.
- I know sometimes it seems like prying.
- It can be very embarrassing.
- I'm not embarrassed.
Good. Very good.
I've been wondering about the lady
you met outside Villette's house.
Quite by chance, I happened
to see you from inside the house.
Inspector, the appointment
that I had with Villette...
...couldn't be of any importance to you.
But we aren't discussing
that at the moment.
You see, with a murder, one has
to jump from one detail to another.
Perhaps I jumped
too suddenly for you.
Well, it seems maybe I don't
follow as fast as you jump.
I have a methodical mind.
I do have to take things one by one.
So do I.
The difficulty, perhaps,
is that, well, we aren't thinking...
...from the same point of view.
Could it be that, Father?
That could be. I don't really know
what your point of view is.
Well, then I've put it badly. Very badly.
Let me try again. Now, this lady
you met outside Villette's house...
I wish I could discuss it, but I can't.
- Who is she?
- She isn't involved.
- That is for me to decide.
- I know, I know...
...but you'll have to take my word for it.
I respect your word,
but I need your help.
I'm not able to help.
I see.
I see, of course.
I just don't want all this mystification
to make things too awkward for you.
Awkward for me?
A priest was seen leaving Villette's
house at the time of the murder.
I saw a priest outside Villette's
house the next morning.
- Well, Father?
- Well?
Too much mystification
might lead one to believe...
...that both priests were one
and the same, mightn't it?
What have you to say?
- What would you want me to say?
- That is up to you, Father.
Well, then, I would say
that a man of intelligence...
...wouldn't be led to believe
anything on so little evidence.
You're perfectly right.
We have checked
on every priest in Quebec.
Each could account for his movements at
the time of the murder, each except one.
Where were you at 11:00, Father?
- I was walking.
- Alone?
- No.
- Good.
Now, if you will just give me
the name and the address of the person.
I can't.
Father...
...don't you wanna help me?
- I've done my best.
- But you refuse to answer my questions.
I'm sorry. I know, l...
It isn't possible for me to answer them.
Then it's a pity...
...a great pity.
Good night, Father.
I'm deeply sorry.
Good night, inspector.
Get me Mr. Robertson.
Yes, the crown prosecutor.
What?
I don't care where he is, find him.
I said, find him wherever he is.
Take it slow. Come on.
Come on.
Lower.
Oh, you have
to get much lower.
Willy, you're wanted on the telephone.
- That's no fair. Leave me alone.
- I'm not kidding. You really are.
Oh, see what they want, Ruth.
All right, Ruth, where are you?
I'll take it.
- You idiot.
- Thank you.
Hello. Yes, this is Robertson.
Oh, it's you, Larrue.
- Fix me a drink?
- Scotch and soda?
Just scotch, no water.
Yes, hello.
You ought to be in bed with a thriller
instead of worrying people.
Yes, yes, I'm listening.
- Drink, darling?
- I'll get it.
What? But aren't you
jumping to conclusions?
Are you sure?
Yes, I see.
Yes. Yes, inspector, yes.
I'll be right over.
Willy, don't look so unhappy.
I can't help it. Murder's not
particularly pleasant.
You should be able to take that in stride.
Not this one.
- Is it about the Villette murder?
- Yes.
And the unpleasant part of it is,
a priest is suspected.
- What nonsense.
- Fantastic, isn't it?
But a priest was actually seen
leaving Villette's house.
Which priest?
Well, Larrue thinks it's Logan
from St. Marie's Church.
- Do you know him?
- I've heard of him.
Well, I must be off. I hate to.
Thanks for a lovely party.
- Good night, Willy.
- Good night, Ruth.
- You'll find your way out, won't you?
- Yes.
- Good night, everybody.
- Good night.
- Ruth...
- We have guests, Pierre.
It was a good party, wasn't it?
- Ruth.
- Yes?
Stop worrying.
- About what?
- Logan. The whole idea is ridiculous.
- Why on earth...?
- Oh, shut up, please. Shut up.
Pierre, I'm sorry.
You're still in love with him.
That should be apparent.
- You never spoke about it.
- Well, I'm not going to talk about it now.
Oh, yes. You are going to speak about it.
I'm not going on like this.
- You don't have to.
- What do you want me to do?
Whatever you wish.
Very simple, isn't it? What does one do
when one's wife is in love with a priest?
- You can leave me.
- How easily you can say that.
I'm not in love with you.
I've never been in love with you.
But I never wanted to believe it.
That's not my fault.
I've never pretended anything with you.
I hope he's in trouble, terrible trouble.
Michael.
My poor Michael.
Hello? I'd like to speak
to Father Logan, please.
Father Logan?
Oh, but he's asleep.
- I'm not asleep.
- It is very late.
I'll take it.
Thank you.
Hello, this is Father Logan.
I've got to see you.
No, I've got to see you.
I can't tell you now. Tomorrow?
No, not at the rectory, please.
Michael, listen. I've got to meet you
somewhere. Anywhere.
Are you listening?
I'm going to Lévis tomorrow morning...
...on the 9:00 ferry.
All right.
Good night.
- Good morning.
- Good morning, Father Logan.
We shouldn't be seen together,
for your sake.
- I had to see you.
- The police have been questioning me.
They saw us talking outside of
Villette's house the other morning.
- They're trying to find out who you are.
- I don't care. I've got to tell you.
- You are being suspected.
- I know that.
You shouldn't be seen talking to me.
There are probably police
all over the boat.
The only thing is for me to tell them
you were with me that night.
- You can't. They'd wanna know why.
- Do you think I care?
I'll tell them everything if I have to.
Ruth, you've got to think of yourself,
think of your husband.
Think of Pierre?
Think of him before I think of you?
- I've never been able to do that.
- You must.
It's too late to think of him.
We spoke of you last night.
He's still in love with me.
I'm not that good.
I love you, Michael.
I've always been in love with you.
I know.
I know it's wrong. I can't help it.
Do you want me to lie to you?
No, I don't want you to lie to me.
- But I don't want you to lie to yourself.
- But I haven't changed, Michael.
I've been married seven years,
and I haven't changed.
Are you afraid of me?
Why?
You're in love with me.
You've always been in love with me.
- You haven't changed.
- Ruth, I've changed.
You've changed too.
You want me to pretend that.
No, I don't want you to pretend.
Ruth, do you understand?
I chose to be what I am.
I believe in what I am.
Michael.
I want you to see things
as they are and not...
And not go on hurting yourself.
Don't pity me.
L... I shan't bother you again.
And you followed her from the ferry
to 22 Grande Allée?
- Yes, sir.
- This is absurd, Larrue.
That is all, Sergeant Farouche.
Murphy, thank you.
This will be very embarrassing for me.
Why should it be, sir?
I'll have to apologize
to Madame Grandfort...
...for this ridiculous report
your men turned in.
I will apologize, sir,
if an apology is necessary.
Very well.
I'll call Madame Grandfort tomorrow.
Why not get it over with, sir?
And then we can get on
with the apologies, if necessary.
Hello, Pierre. This is Willy.
Oh, no. No.
Is Ruth there? Yes, please.
Hello, Ruth.
I see.
Yes, I understand. Yes. Of course.
That's very kind of you. Thank you.
What does Willy want?
He wants me to come to his office now.
May I ask you why?
I was seen on the ferry this morning
with Michael Logan.
Apparently, I was followed
by a detective.
Could you have picked
a less public place if you had to see...?
I'm sorry.
Would you like to tell me
what you're going to do?
I'm going to answer whatever questions
the inspector wishes to ask me.
I'm also going to explain that Michael
could not have killed Villette.
Has Father Logan cleared himself
to your satisfaction?
He didn't have to.
I was with him at the time.
Would you like me to go with you?
I'm in no position to ask
any favors of you, Pierre.
- Monsieur and Madame Grandfort.
- Do come in.
I'm extremely grateful that
you are both cooperative.
- Ruth, Pierre, I'm terribly sorry.
- It's perfectly all right.
Larrue promises to keep it
from the press.
I will do my best.
Sit down, please.
- Father Logan's outside.
- Bring him in. Come in.
I've asked Father Logan to join us.
Father Logan...
...Madame and Monsieur Grandfort,
Mr. Robertson.
- Me, you know.
- Good evening, Father Logan.
- Good evening.
- Sit down.
Thank you.
- May we begin, please?
- Well, Madame Grandfort...
What do you wish to know?
You met and talked with Father Logan
on the 9:00 ferry.
- Yes.
- May I ask the reason for this meeting?
I don't think the reason
could help you, inspector.
- It was personal?
- Yes.
Very well.
You also met and spoke
with Father Logan...
...the morning after Villette's murder.
You met and spoke to him
immediately in front of Villette's house.
- Yes.
- May I ask the reason for that?
I had an appointment
with Monsieur Villette.
- He was your lawyer?
- No.
Father Logan, knowing of the murder,
stopped you from entering the house?
- Yes.
- Of course, he did not know...
...you had an appointment
with Monsieur Villette.
He did. The night before, I'd had
an appointment with Father Logan.
I told him I was going to meet Monsieur
Villette at 9:30 the following morning.
You had an appointment
with Father Logan...
...the night Monsieur Villette
was murdered?
- Yes.
- Where?
- We took a ride in my car.
- What time?
Between 9 and 11.
Madame Grandfort.
- Are you sure of the time?
- Oh, yes.
I got home just after 11. My husband
had come in five minutes before.
That's right, inspector.
You told your husband, of course,
that you had just seen Father Logan?
No, I did not tell my husband.
Was there any particular reason
why you shouldn't have told him?
- Yes.
- Inspector, I beg you.
Consider if your line of questioning
has to be so personal.
That is for me to decide, Father.
- Madame Grandfort?
- Yes?
You understand I must
ask these questions.
Yes. I came to tell that you...
...Father Logan could not have been
involved in Villette's death.
I was with him at the time.
I have accepted everything
that you have said, madame.
But I must know, if possible...
...the reason for your appointment
with Monsieur Villette.
Monsieur Villette was blackmailing me.
I had met Father Logan to ask his advice.
You hadn't told
your husband about this?
- It was...
- It was what, madame?
It was nothing to do with my husband.
- Surely he would have been concerned.
- Yes. You see, that was it.
- I didn't want to worry him.
- So you turned to Father Logan.
- Yes.
- Is Father Logan your parish priest?
- No.
- No?
Yet you turned to him for advice when
you wouldn't turn to your husband.
- Father Logan is an old friend.
- And he advised you to tell your husband.
No, how could he? He couldn't do that.
Before your first appointment
with Father Logan...
...he knew you were being blackmailed?
Oh, how could he?
I hadn't seen him in years.
You hadn't seen him in years, and yet
you say he was an old friend.
Mr. Larrue.
- Inspector?
- Yes, sir?
My wife doesn't have to
answer those questions.
She's not under oath.
Your wife was seen outside
Villette's house with Father Logan.
She was seen this morning
with Father Logan.
She told us of an appointment
with him that took place...
...the night Monsieur Villette
was murdered.
Surely, Monsieur Grandfort...
...you do not want your wife
to implicate herself further.
It is you who are trying to implicate her.
My wife came here to answer questions
and to clear, as far as possible...
...Father Logan of any suspicions.
She has done both of those things.
Madame Grandfort,
why were you being blackmailed?
You don't need to answer that.
Why shouldn't she, Father?
- What are you afraid of?
- It isn't necessary. Don't answer.
Madame Grandfort,
are you trying to protect Father Logan?
From what? He hasn't done anything.
It would seem as if he had.
Are you a human being, inspector?
You think it's important
for me to tell you...
...why I was being blackmailed.
You don't care whom I hurt, just so long
as I answer all your questions.
- I only want to clear a murder.
- Yes, I know.
You only want everything clear.
And I want to clear Father Logan.
- Ruth.
- Willy.
May I have a glass of water, please?
Ruth.
Pierre, why must you hear
what I'm going to say?
Thank you, Willy.
Inspector...
...the blackmail was about
me and Father Logan.
Father Logan and I grew up together.
Have you ever been young, inspector?
Of course, you know
that the first thing is to fall in love.
If we'd been engaged,
it wouldn't have mattered...
...because the war came.
He was one of the first to volunteer.
I hated him for that.
I was selfish even then.
He took things so seriously.
War. And love.
Yes, even love.
Because when I said
we ought to get married...
... he said there were enough
widows already.
He said he loved me too much.
He didn 't know
he could never love me enough.
That night, we went dancing.
It was our last evening together.
It was all too short.
That was the night Michael went away.
I thought the world was coming
to an end.
I suppose there were millions of people
feeling the same way that night.
You don 't think of millions of people.
You think of yourself...
... and the one you're in love with.
He asked me not to wait for him.
A lot of other boys must've said
the same thing to their girls.
I had to wait for him.
His letters were long at first,
but always serious.
I didn 't want serious letters...
... but I would prefer those
to no letters at all.
Because...
... after a while...
... he stopped writing.
Soon afterward...
... I started working
for my future husband.
Pierre was...
Madame Grandfort,
perhaps if you are unable to continue...
It's all right. L...
I'm sorry.
Pierre was always so brilliant.
He was kind.
He realized I was unhappy.
And like very kind people...
... he didn 't ask me why.
He just tried to amuse me.
We got married.
I was happy.
I was through with...
I thought I was through with...
... you know...
Well. Oh, yes...
... it was at my wedding
that I saw Villette for the first time.
Then the war was over.
The men were coming home.
I knew the day
when he would come home.
On that day, I went down to the port.
A boat had just come in.
Suddenly, I saw him.
He had changed, I suppose...
... but I didn 't notice.
We arranged to meet the next day.
It was a lovely day.
The end of summer.
Michael talked and talked.
He told me all the thoughts
that had come to him during the war.
I didn 't want to hear about the war.
But the war had changed him.
Then a storm came up, so suddenly.
We saw a house across the field
and ran for shelter.
The house was closed.
I don 't know what time it was.
But it was late.
We had missed the last ferry
back from the island.
There was no way I could
get in touch with my husband.
It stopped raining in the morning.
A man came walking down
through the garden.
He walked as though he owned it.
As a matter of fact, he did.
I was still in the summerhouse...
... and he didn 't know who I was...
... but apparently,
he knew I was a woman...
... because he made some remark
to Michael.
Michael knocked him down.
I came out and stood on the steps of
the summerhouse, looked down at him.
He looked up at me and said:
"Good morning, Madame Grandfort."
It was Villette.
What could I say to Michael?
I hadn 't told him I was married.
I didn't see him again for five years.
Nor did I see Villette again,
until the day Michael was ordained.
Then I began running into Villette...
... all the time.
He appeared everywhere I went.
One day in Parliament,
I was listening to Pierre.
Villette came up to me.
He said that he was in trouble.
Something to do with a tax scandal.
Only my husband could help him.
I told him Pierre would never
get involved in anything shady.
Then he threatened
to tell about Michael and me.
What words could I say that would
tell him it was wrong about us?
Pierre's career would be finished.
Michael might be unfrocked.
I tried to ignore him,
but he kept after me...
... kept calling up.
Then one day, I ran into him again.
And he gave me 24 hours...
... or else.
Oh, I was really desperate by then.
Then I thought
that maybe Michael might help...
... and I rang him up.
We met that same night.
He was very angry.
He said not to worry about Villette...
... that he would deal with him.
And we arranged to meet the next day
in front of Villette's house.
I went there at 9:30.
I wondered at the crowds.
Then Michael told me Villette was dead.
I couldn 't believe it.
I was free.
Well, inspector?
May my wife leave now?
Certainly.
Father Logan has his alibi now,
doesn't he, Willy?
Of course.
Thank you.
Would you like to go now, Father?
- Good night.
Good night, Father.
Well, it's over.
Is it, sir?
- Yes. Let's get out of here.
- Look, sir.
- What's that?
- The autopsy report.
Villette had dinner in a restaurant at 9.
Examining his stomach...
...the doctors found that he couldn't
have died before 11:30.
Larrue.
Madame Grandfort said that
she left Father Logan at 11.
You can do a lot of things in 30 minutes.
- Who is it?
- Pierre.
Come in.
- Sorry I woke you.
- I was awake.
Willy Robertson just called.
He's coming over.
What an odd time to pay us a visit.
Must be very early.
I'm afraid he's coming here officially.
Officially?
The statement you made last night,
it wasn't helpful...
...at least not... Not in the way
you hoped it to be.
But I told the truth.
No one doubts what you said.
I don't see...
You said you left Father Logan at 11:00.
Now they have established
that Villette was murdered at 11:30.
There's a time lag of half an hour.
Did they know about this time lag?
Did they know
before they questioned me?
Why did the inspector
allow me to say all those things?
There was no need for my statement.
- Why is Willy coming here?
- I asked him.
I want him to talk to you.
You may be called as a witness.
A witness?
- Are they going to arrest Michael?
- Yes.
But he hasn't done anything.
He had no reason to.
- Why should they think he killed Villette?
- Your statement answered that.
My statement?
He says you have given the motive
they've been waiting for.
I...
I should have lied, Pierre.
I lied before.
I should have lied last night.
They'll twist what I've said.
They'll turn it, they'll use it.
I've given them what they wanted.
I was going to help Michael...
...but I've destroyed him.
And you, Pierre...
What have I done to you?
Willy will soon be here.
You must have your breakfast.
Would you like it here, in your room?
I will send it up.
You must do something.
They're going to arrest you.
Michael, what can we do?
I don't know.
You're not going to let them
bring you to trial?
You understand what that would mean.
You can't let that happen.
Michael...
I've done this to you.
There must be something I can do.
There's nothing we can do.
- I beg your pardon. I'm so sorry.
- It was my fault, madame.
I've been waiting to speak to you,
Father.
You have been talking to the police, yes?
What did the police ask you, Father?
They asked about me.
You told them about me.
I'm going to be arrested, Keller.
You?
Why would they arrest you, Father?
You're trying to frighten me. You think
by telling me that, I will give myself up.
You think I am easily frightened
after what I did?
So, what are you going to do
when they arrest you?
Perhaps you'll point your finger at me.
Perhaps you'll say, "It's Keller."
That's what you will do, is it? You are
a coward after all. You are frightened.
Maybe they will hang you instead of me,
and that frightens you.
Perhaps you will tell them. You can't
tell them as long as you are a priest.
Can you?
The priest is frightened, Alma.
You saw the look on his face?
He thinks he can tell the police, yes?
I am ready.
I'd like to speak
with Father Logan, please.
- Father Logan is not here.
- Good morning.
I came to see Father Logan,
but Keller says he's not here.
Not here?
He didn't say he was going out.
- He didn't say anything to me.
- I saw him.
I tried to speak to him.
He seemed frightened.
I asked him if I could do anything.
He didn't even hear me.
He went out by that door
20 minutes ago, maybe 30.
Thank you. I'll be back, Father.
All right, Murphy, what is it?
What?
Stand by outside the rectory.
Logan is gone.
Give me the radio room.
Will Father Logan be in for lunch?
I don't know.
Any news yet?
All right.
Hello, Father.
- Have you had your lunch yet?
- No.
Let me order something for you.
Mr. Murphy,
where did you find this cassock?
In a patent-leather trunk.
Would you be able to say if
the trunk belonged to the accused?
I would say that it did.
His initials, "M.W.L.," were on the trunk.
The trunk was in his room.
Would you say that the cassock
had been hidden in the trunk?
Did it seem as though placed
so as to escape detection?
Well, there were a lot
of other things covering it.
A raincoat, a pair of galoshes
and several books.
- Thank you. Your witness.
- No questions.
That's all. Thank you.
Call Dr. Bonnard.
The evidence you give
shall be the truth, the whole truth...
...and nothing but the truth.
- I swear.
- Your name?
- Georges Bonnard.
- Your age, please?
- Forty-two.
- Your occupation?
- Pathologist.
- You're a professor at Laval University?
- I am.
- You have examined these stains?
- I have, sir.
- Would you tell the court what they are?
- They're human blood.
- Would you tell us what blood type?
- Type O, sir.
Is this the same blood type
as that of the murdered man?
- It is, sir.
- Thank you, doctor.
On the night of the murder,
you spoke to the accused?
At what time did your conversation
take place?
A little after 11:45, sir.
Would you tell the court of the events
that led up to this conversation?
Yes, sir.
My wife was asleep, sir,
and I was just about to go to bed.
I happened to look out the window,
and I saw someone enter the church.
I couldn't tell who it was
at that distance...
...so I went downstairs
and through the passageway...
...that connects the rectory
to the church.
The light was dim, sir,
but I could see someone...
...who was kneeling
against the altar rail.
As he lifted his head...
...I recognized Father Logan, sir.
Was there anything about his manner
that seemed out of the ordinary?
He seemed...
...distressed, sir.
- Did you speak to him?
- Yes, sir. I asked him if he were ill.
He said no. He said I should go back
and leave him alone.
- But you didn't leave him immediately?
- No, sir.
Why was that?
Father Logan had always been very kind
to my wife and to me...
...so I wanted to help him if I could.
He seemed to need help?
He seemed very, very distressed, sir.
And he wouldn't let you help him?
No, sir. He said to me again,
"Go back, Keller. Leave me alone."
So I went back to my room.
You spoke to your wife
of this incident?
No, sir.
- Why not?
- She was asleep, sir.
And also I didn't like
to talk about it.
It didn't seem right to me...
...to mention such distress
as Father Logan's to anyone.
It seemed a very private distress, sir.
I'm only trying to clarify
your testimony.
I've told you everything
you need to know.
That is hardly for you to decide.
Madame Grandfort, will you please
answer my questions, "yes" or "no"?
Some questions cannot
be answered that way.
Well, I'll try to rephrase it.
I'll try to help you.
Is it true that you had an association
with the accused...
...which you didn't wish
to become public knowledge?
You're twisting my words.
You haven't listened to me.
The witness will confine herself
to answer as to the facts.
Madame Grandfort, let me repeat
your answer to my earlier question.
You said that you were in love with
the accused before the war. Am I right?
Yes.
Then were you in love with him...
...at the time of your marriage
to Monsieur Grandfort?
- I object, my lord.
- I refuse to answer.
- You have no right.
- Objection overruled.
We have your signed testimony
as to your relationship.
Do you wish that testimony
read to this court?
Then were you in love
with the accused...
...at the time of your marriage
to Monsieur Grandfort?
- Yes.
- And still in love with him...
...on the night of the murder?
Yes.
Then isn't it possible that you met
with him between the night...
...at the summerhouse and the night
Villette was killed?
I did not.
You can hardly expect
the jury to believe...
...that a woman in love doesn't
attempt to meet her lover.
I object, my lord.
This line of questioning
doesn't seem particularly relevant.
It is, my lord. I'm trying
to establish a motive for the murder.
I'm trying to discover
if Villette's blackmail...
...was based on his knowledge
not merely of one night at his home...
...but also of a continuous,
uninterrupted, illicit...
- No, that's not true! Not true!
- Silence! Silence!
Father Logan, will you
examine this garment?
Is this your cassock?
No, sir.
- Then did you borrow this cassock?
- No.
It's not yours,
and you did not borrow it.
And yet it was found in your trunk.
- Someone must have put it there.
- Yes.
Have you any idea who might have
put this cassock in your trunk?
I can't say.
Father Logan, when did you decide
to become a priest?
After the war.
In becoming a priest, were you,
perhaps, trying to hide from something?
I had never thought of the priesthood
as offering a hiding place.
I understand you to mean that priesthood
involves certain responsibilities...
...certain moralities.
- Yes.
You were aware of these
responsibilities, these moralities?
Yes.
Yet you saw nothing wrong...
...in having a clandestine meeting
with a woman?
Are you trying to imply that I was
a priest at that time? I was not.
Did you take into consideration
that this woman was married?
I wasn't aware that she was.
And so you spent the whole day
with this woman?
Yes. We were good friends.
I hadn't seen her in over two years.
Such good friends that you spent
the night with her?
- We were caught in a storm.
- Oh, the storm was the villain.
Did you warn Madame Grandfort that
her husband might not agree on that?
As I said,
I didn't know she was married.
On discovering that she was...
...did you make any attempt to explain
the situation to Monsieur Grandfort?
No.
But surely there is
some contradiction...
...between this secretiveness
and your vocation.
I saw nothing wrong
with being caught in a storm.
If there was nothing wrong...
...why did you have such a violent
argument with Villette the next morning?
Were you anxious to protect
Madame Grandfort's reputation?
Yes.
Then her reputation was in danger?
You realized there was something more
than merely being caught in the storm?
Villette made an insinuation.
My argument with Villette had nothing
to do with any sudden realization.
- And you hit him?
- Yes, I did.
- In anger?
- Yes.
You're capable of hitting a man...
...who merely intrudes
upon a harmless situation.
Then surely you are capable
of far more violent action...
...when that same man blackmails
your good friend Madame Grandfort.
- I'm not capable of murder.
- You would allow such a man...
...to destroy Madame Grandfort's home
and your career?
No.
You would go to such a man and,
unable to control your temper...
...unable to face a public scandal,
you'd turn to physical force.
No, I would not!
Silence! Silence!
You and Madame Grandfort separated
at 11:00 on the night of the murder.
That's right. Yes.
Then it was possible for you
to go to Villette's house.
It was possible for you to arrive there
at 11:30, the time he was murdered.
Yes, it was possible,
but I didn't go there.
I went right home to the rectory.
And what time did you arrive
at the rectory?
About 11: 15.
- Did anybody witness this arrival?
- I don't believe so.
You say you arrived at 11: 15.
- What did you do then?
- I went up to my room.
- You went to bed immediately?
- No.
- What did you do?
- I went into the church.
- Did you see anybody there?
- Otto Keller.
Otto Keller has testified
to this court that he followed you...
...and that he found you kneeling
before the altar in great distress.
He has further testified that the time
was then 11:45 or after.
Well, it could have been 11:45.
The rest isn't true.
Perhaps you are prepared,
at last, to tell us the truth.
It might have been 11:45.
The rest is not true.
Perhaps you are prepared
to give us your version of the truth.
Of course you refuse to answer...
...because I submit you did not return
to the rectory at 11: 15.
You did not return
until 11:45 or after.
Your distress, seen by Otto Keller,
was caused by the fact...
...that you had earlier met with
Villette and been threatened by him...
...with exposure of your affair
with Madame Grandfort.
And that you'd taken the first weapon
you found and struck Villette...
...and continued to strike
until you cracked his skull wide open.
No!
I repeat, it's your duty...
...to carefully examine
all the evidence that's been given...
...and to determine whether the charge
against the accused has been proven.
Remember also that you are not
trying the accused...
...for whatever views you may hold...
...as to his relationship
with Madame Grandfort...
...except as it may affect
this charge of murder.
One final point.
The fact that the accused
is a priest under holy orders...
...should not influence your verdict
one way or the other.
You may now withdraw
to consider your verdict.
But I believe what
the prosecutor said.
Obviously, they didn't spend
just that one night together.
There must have been many more times.
Gentlemen of the jury,
are you agreed on your verdict?
- And who will speak for you?
- We are.
How say you? Is Michael William Logan
guilty of murder or not guilty?
While we attach grave suspicion
to the accused...
...we cannot find sufficient evidence
to prove...
...he actually wielded the weapon
that killed Monsieur Villette.
Therefore, our verdict is not guilty.
Hearken to your verdict
as the court recorded it.
You say Michael William Logan
is not guilty, so you say all.
- Yes.
- I said that cassock...
- They've ruined him.
Why couldn't they have said
"not guilty" and let it go at that?
Your Lordship, I move that
the prisoner be released.
Michael Logan, while I have
no doubt that the jury...
...must have reached their conclusion
in utmost fairness...
...and solemn regard for justice...
...I cannot help expressing my personal
disagreement with their verdict.
Michael William Logan,
you are hereby discharged.
Everybody stand up.
Michael.
Take off that collar!
Preach us a sermon, Logan!
Are you satisfied, Willy?
Are you satisfied with all this?
Do you think I've enjoyed it?
Alma. Alma!
Alma, come here! Alma!
Alma...
Stop it!
He's innocent.
My husb...
There he goes!
In the hotel.
All right. Quick, get a doctor.
It hurts.
- Could we move her inside?
- She should not be moved at all.
She shouted something. What is it
you were shouting, Mrs. Keller?
She said he was innocent.
- Villette...
- Villette?
What about Villette, Mrs. Keller?
What? What is it?
What is she saying?
She says, "Forgive me."
- Mr. Larrue.
- Have you got Keller?
He just ran
in the Chateau Frontenac, sir.
Get Farouche and his squad.
Corrigan too.
- Murphy, I do not want him to be shot.
- But, sir, he's got a gun.
I know, I know. I don't want him dead.
I want to talk to him.
- She's gone.
- Come along, Father.
- Now, what about this Keller?
- What do you mean?
He shot his wife. What was she doing?
Was she trying to warn you or save you?
Keller works as Villette's gardener.
He also works in the rectory.
- What more can you tell me about him?
- Let me try and talk to him, inspector.
Talk to him, sure. Go ahead.
But where is he?
Couldn't we have one entrance open?
At least one?
No. No. Keep these people right where
they are for their own safety, please.
Start in the basement
and work your way up.
Remember, I said, no shooting.
Now, go ahead.
Get an ambulance at once.
Well, he just shot a man,
a chef in the kitchen.
Now will you tell me anything
about him, Father?
Father, what are you trying to do?
Protect this Keller?
He's on the mezzanine going upstairs.
In the ballroom.
Tell Larrue.
Keller! Give yourself up!
Stay back!
Have them send over some tear gas.
- Keller!
- Inspector, let me go in.
Let me try and talk to him.
No.
- Keller!
- What do you want, inspector?
I want you to give yourself up.
- Why would I do that?
- Haven't you done enough harm?
I could do more, inspector.
You've already shot two people.
Isn't that enough?
And what about Villette?
- Villette?
- Yes, what about Villette?
So the priest talked.
Hey, Logan!
Where are you, Father Logan?
Keller.
There you are.
My only friend, Father Logan.
How kindly he hears my confession...
...and then a little shame,
a little violence...
...that's all it takes
to make him talk.
It was too much for you, huh?
You are a coward
like all other people, aren't you?
A hypocrite like all the rest.
Pierre, take me home.
Frank, try to get him in the shoulder,
make him drop that gun.
- It'd be easier to get him in the leg.
- His shoulder. The right shoulder.
- We're going to shoot now, Keller.
- Don't make them do it!
Father, don't go in...
Coming to speak to me?
Put the gun away. There's been
enough bloodshed already.
You must not come closer, Father.
I'll shoot you, you know.
You won't shoot me, Otto.
Why will I not shoot you?
Because you call me Otto...
...in such a friendly way,
like Alma used to call me Otto?
Where is my Alma?
- She's dead.
- No.
- You killed her.
- It is your fault.
Oh, I loved her.
It made me cry to see her work so hard.
Those poor hands.
Such beautiful hands.
- She can't be dead.
- She is.
Then I am as alone as you are.
- I'm not alone.
- Oh, yes, you are.
To kill you now
would be a favor to you.
You have no friends.
What has happened
to your friends, Father?
They mob you. They call at you.
It would be better
if you were as guilty as I am.
Then they would shoot you quickly...
...and you mustn't suffer much.
Look...
Oh, Father.
Help me. Quickly.
- Get the hotel doctor.
- And the ambulance?
Forgive me.